Guide to the Stanford University, Center for International Security and Cooperation, Records SC1058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Center for International Security and Cooperation, records
1970-2013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Center for International Security and Cooperation
SC1058
13.75 Linear Feet and 33382.4megabytes
Scope and Contents
The History Project records include organizational files, files about Fellows, and biographical files about visiting speakers. Audiovisual material is comprised of recordings of CISAC workshops and conferences recorded on audiocassettes and VHS videocassettes. Restricled Files include donor information, salary information, recommendations, endorsements, reviews, etc.
Biographical/Historical note
The Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC), part of the Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies (FSI), is an interdisciplinary university-based research and training center addressing some of the world's most difficult security problems with policy-relevant solutions. The Center is committed to scholarly research and to giving independent advice to governments and international organizations.
The Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC) traces its origins to the Vietnam War and the mass teach-ins that took place on campus during that turbulent era. At one of the gatherings, political scientist John Lewis, a noted China scholar, met physicist Wolfgang (Pief) Panofsky, then director of the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC), and Stanford law Professor John Barton. The three men, Lewis recalled, found that the students had little knowledge about war and how security policies are developed. In response, the scholars decided to create a teaching environment in which students from different disciplines could examine international security matters and understand how government policy is formed.
In 1970, their class, "Arms Control and Disarmament," focused on nuclear weapons and efforts to control them through treaties and negotiations. Today, the descendant of that class is still team-taught by CISAC faculty every winter quarter under the name, "International Security in a Changing World." Over time, this course has influenced thousands of Stanford undergraduates.
In 1973, the Ford Foundation awarded Stanford a grant to develop a course on arms control and an accompanying textbook. International Arms Control: Issues and Agreements (subsequently published in two editions; the second, edited by Coit Blacker and Gloria Duffy, became the standard textbook on the subject.) A year later, the foundation gave the fledgling program a five-year grant for training, research and outreach activities. In 1978, along with three other university-based centers, Stanford's "Arms Control Program" received Ford Foundation endowment funds that Stanford subsequently matched. When the match was finalized in 1983, Stanford's Center for International Security and Arms Control (CISAC) was established. John Lewis and SLAC physicist Sidney Drell were the Center's first two co-directors, a structure maintained ever since.
From early in its history, CISAC emphasized a three-part mission, which continues today:
To produce policy-relevant research on international security problems; To teach and train the next generation of security specialists; To influence policymaking in international security.
From inception, the Center focused on the study of U.S.-Soviet-China relations, arms control and nonproliferation, and the technical aspects of international security issues. In 1983, Carnegie Corporation of New York gave CISAC a grant to bring mid-career scientists to the Center to work on international security issues. Ever since, CISAC has brought scientists, social scientists and policy experts to the Center as fellows.
After Soviet Premier Mikhail Gorbachev came to power in 1985, CISAC was able to foster deeper ties with the Soviet academic and policy-making communities. In 1990, when Gorbachev visited Stanford and gave a lecture on cooperation and reconciliation between the two longtime adversaries, he singled out the efforts of Stanford and CISAC researchers in bridging Cold War hostilities.
The end of the Cold War reduced many security dangers but increased others. As new challenges emerged, CISAC's research agenda adapted accordingly. New areas of study included the safeguarding of nuclear weapons and the study of internal and regional wars, peacekeeping operations, and peace settlements.
In 1998, CISAC moved to larger quarters in Encina Hall and changed its name--in reflection of its broadened mandate--to the Center for International Security and Cooperation. The Center continued to mentor visiting fellows and expanded its teaching activities by establishing an undergraduate honors program in international security studies in 2000.
After the terrorist attacks on 9/11, the center's research agenda broadened again to include questions of terrorism and counterterrorism. Work at the Center continues to reflect the ongoing and emerging security challenges worldwide. For example, senior scholar-practitioners such as CISAC'S William Perry and George Shultz at Hoover, the center's first co-directors Sid Drell and John Lewis, former visiting scholar James Goodby, and faculty members David Holloway and Scott Sagan--are working with a vision to eliminate nuclear weapons worldwide, with a focus on practical steps that can be taken now.
From its roots in the teach-ins of the Vietnam War, CISAC's mission continues to focus on making useful and relevant contributions to peace and security. By promoting cross-disciplinary research that tackles complex challenges in innovative ways, by training the next generation of security experts and by using knowledge to influence policymakers, CISAC works for a safer, more secure world.
Access to Collection
Restricted files closed until January 1, 2086. Otherwise the collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged in five series: 1. Administrative Records; 2. Audiovisual Material; 3. History Project Records; 4. Restricted Files; 5. Photographs.
Provenance
The materials were transferred from the Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC), 2011.
International relations -- Congresses.; International law -- Congresses.; International relations -- Study and teaching.; International relations.; Security, International.; Stanford University. Center for International Security and Cooperation
- Administrative records
  - External review, 2008 Dec 4-5 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Strategic planning retreat, 2008 Oct 22 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Audiovisual material
  - Welcome and Introduction: Dr. O. E. Jones and Dr. R. L. Rinne, Day One, Tape 1., 2.1; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Panel I: BG. Richardson, J. Morse, Prof. York, Prof. Bowne, Day One, Tape 4., 2.2; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Panel I: BG. Richardson, J. Morse, Prof. York, Prof. Bowne, Day One, Tape 5., 2.3; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - The Interplay among TNF Policy Studies and Exercises. Mr. Phillip A Karber. Day One, Tape 6A., 2.4; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - The Interplay among TNF Policy Studies and Exercises. Mr. Phillip A Karber. Day One, Tape 6B., 2.5; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - TNF and the Berlin Crises. Ms. Kori Schake, Day Two, Tape 1., 2.6; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - The Sword and Shield Strategy of the Early 1960s: Gen. Johannes Steinhoff (Ret.), Day Two, Tape 2., 2.7; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Panel II: Prof. C. M. Kelleher, Grig. Gen. R.C. Richardson, Gov. Steinhoff, Amb. S. Weiss, Day Two, Tape 3., 2.8; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Panel II: Questions and Answers, Day Two, Tape 4., 2.9; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Panel: Dr. R Pfaltzgraff (Interviewer), Dr. L. Davis, Gen. D. Starry, Gen. W. Smith, Dr. J. Thompson, Dr. R. Wagner, Day Three, Tape 2A., 2.10; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - The Evolution of Soviet TNF Thinking, Maj. Gen. E. B. Atkeson (Ret.), Day Three, Tape 3., 2.11; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Studies, Analysis, and Exercise Influence on TNF Requirements, Mr. R. Stivers, Day Three, Tape 4, 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - US Nuclear Weapons in Europe: A German Perspective, 1996 Aug 26; 2.13; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - US Nuclear Weapons in Central Europe: Prospects and Priorities, Prof. David S. Yost, 1996 Aug 20; 2.14; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Nuclear Risk Communication Workshop, Tape 1, 2.15; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
  - Nuclear Risk Communication Workshop, Tape 3, 2002 May 20; 2.16; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
  - Nuclear Risk Communication Workshop, Tape 5, 2.17; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
  - The Face of Battle, 2011
- History Project records
  - Mailings to Members (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Drell, Sidney- Resignation (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drell, Sidney - papers, presentations (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Goodby, James - articles and papers (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Goodby, James - articles and papers (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Goodby, James - Payne Lectureship (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shultz, George (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shultz, George, Hoover/US (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Perlman, David (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bio - M. Granger Morgan, Carnegie Mellon/US (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bio - Ken Sheely, DOE/US (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bio - V. S. Arunachalam, Carnegie Mellon/US (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bio - Steven Aoki, DOS/US (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bill Desmond - DOE/US (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Matthew Bunn, Harvard US (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fissile Materials Workshop - Workshop Substance, 1997 Jul (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Vladimir Sukhoruckin (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bio - Lothar Kock, Germany/EU (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kun Jai Lee, ROK (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bio - Gennady Pshakin, Russia (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Laura Holgate - DOD/US (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bio - John Immele, DOE/US (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Yuri Volodin, Russia (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fissile Materials Workshop (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bio - Zafar Iqbal Cheema - Pakistan (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Roger Howsley - UK (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bio - Hiroyoshi Kurihara, Japan (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Anselmo Paschoa, Brazil (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bruno Pellaud, Austria/IAEA (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - S. Rajagopal, INDIA (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bio - Gotthard Stein, GERMANY (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bio - Zhang Xingqian (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Managing Military Uranium and Plutonium in the United States and the Former Soviet Union, by Matthew Bunn and John P. HOldren (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Managing Military Uranium and Plutonium in the United States and the Former Soviet Union, by Matthew Bunn and John P. Holdren (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Adlai Stevenson III (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Adlai Stevenson III (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Adlai Stevenson III (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hon. Motoo Shiina (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Henry Rowen (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Restricted files
  Scope and Contents
  Files include donor information, salary information, recommendations, endorsements, reviews, etc. Restricted until January 1, 2086.
  Access to Collection
  Restricted 75 years from date of creation.
  - Abrams, Herbert (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Duffey, Gloria (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - George, Alexander (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Goodby, James appointments, 85 and 89, 1985, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Goodby, James, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Goodby, James evaluation: Snr. Res. Scholar, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Goodby, James, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - Panofsky, Wolfgang (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Oskenberg, Michel (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rice, Condoleezza (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Titarenko, Mikhail (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Photographs, 1990-2013
  - Photograph albums
    - CISAC Events, 1997 Oct (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - CISAC Events, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - CISAC Events, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - CISAC Events (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - CISAC Events, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Portraits, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - CISAC Events, 2000 Mar (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - CISAC Events (1 of 2), 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - CISAC Events (2 of 2 ), 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - CISAC Events, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - CISAC Events, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - CISAC Events, Part II (1 of 2), 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - CISAC Events, Part II (2 of 2), 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - CISAC, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - CISAC, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - CISAC Events, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - CISAC Events, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - CISAC Events, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - CISAC Photos, 2007-2008 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - CISAC Events, 2006-2007 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - CISAC, 2006-2007 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - CISAC Photos, 2005-2006 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - CISAC, 2004-2005 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Photos, 2010-2013 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Photos (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Sally Ride (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Ride, Sally.
    - New Century Seminar, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - CISAC, 2008-2009 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Born-digital images, 2009-2012
    - CISAC ambassadors, 2012 Feb 1; 376 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - CISAC honors ceremony
      - 2011 Jun 14, 92 computer file(s) (jpg)
      - 2012 Jun 16, 101 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - CISAC people
      - 2009 Dec 2
        - Carlin, Robert, 2009 Dec 2
        - Crenshaw, Martha, 2009 Dec 2
        - Diffie, Whitfield, 2009 Dec 2
        - Flynn, Stephen E., 2009 Dec 2
        - Richardson, Jeffery H., 2009 Dec 2
      - 2011 Sep
      - 2012 Dep 24
      - 2013 Sep 30
    - Cyber security, 2012 Jan 13; 112 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - Drell Lecture
      The Drell Lecture is an annual public event sponsored by CISAC. By tradition, the Drell lecturer addresses a current and critical national or international security issue that has important scientific or technical dimensions. The Drell Lecture is named for Sidney Drell, CISAC's founding science co-director. Albert and Cicely Wheelon generously endowed the lectureship.
      - Sherman, Nancy. The Moral Wounds of War: The War Within, 2011 Sep 22; 73 computer file(s) (jpg)
        The author of the acclaimed The Untold War: Inside the Hearts, Minds, and Souls of Our Soldiers provides a unique analysis of the moral weight of warfare through the lenses of philosophy and psychology.
      - Thirteen Days -- and Fifty Years Later: What Have We Learned from the Cuban Missile Crisis?, 2012 Sep 22; 90 computer file(s) (jpg)
        Fifty years ago, the Soviet Union and the United States stood on the brink of nuclear war. For thirteen days in October 1962, people around the world held their breath and hoped for a peaceful resolution to the Cuban Missile Crisis. This distinguished panel will discuss and debate the crisis from the perspectives of Moscow and Washington, and consider what history has taught us since those thirteen days in 1962.
        SPEAKERS David Holloway - CISAC, History, and Political Science, Stanford Scott D. Sagan - CISAC and Political Science, Stanford Strobe Talbott - President, Brookings Institution Joe Cirincione (moderator) - President, Ploughshares Fund
    - Ethics of the Draft, 2010 Dec 2; 92 computer file(s) (jpg)
      SPEAKERS David Kennedy - History, Emeritus at Stanford Eliot Cohen - Strategic Studies at Johns Hopkins Jean Bethke Elshtain - Social and Political Ethics at University of Chicago Divinity School Scott D. Sagan (moderator) - (Moderator) Political Science at Stanford
      Should citizens be required to serve their country by fighting for it? Do we think differently about the decision to go to war when only a small number of citizens will fight it? Do volunteer armies and draft armies fight differently in combat?
      This panel discussion focuses on the draft versus the volunteer army in the U.S. Our distinguished panelists examine "who should fight" in a democracy, focusing on the ethical dimension of a state's system of military service.
      Who should fight? It is no idle question in an era in which thousands of U.S. troops are fighting and dying in Afghanistan and Iraq to protect Americans back home. In fact, the answer has profound consequences for the way policymakers make decisions about how these wars are waged. On Dec. 2, scholars from Stanford, the University of Chicago, and the School of Advanced International Studies at Johns Hopkins University examined this issue as part of the Stanford Ethics & War Series, co-sponsored by the Center for International Security and Cooperation. Their conclusion: there is a wide and troubling divide between the 2.4 million Americans who volunteer to serve in the military and the many millions more who choose not to.
      The statistics are revealing: During World War II, some 16 million men, and several thousand women, served in the military, representing 12 percent of the U.S. population. They came from all walks of life, and those who stayed home made sacrifices of their own for the greater war effort. But while the U.S. population has more than doubled since then, the military is now just 4 percent of the size it was in the 1940s. At the same time, today's wars require virtually no sacrifice at home, and those who enlist come from an extremely narrow demographic segment of the U.S. population. According to Stanford historian David Kennedy, who spoke at the event, in 2007, only 2.6 percent of enlisted personnel had exposure to college, compared to 32 percent of men age 18 to 24 in the general population. The military is disproportionately composed of racial, ethnic, and other demographic minorities, he noted. The political elites making the decisions about warfare seldom have children serving. Among the 535 elected members of Congress in 2008 only 10 had children in the military.
      The implications of this are vast. A lack of personal familiarity for many Americans with the military breeds to some puzzling behavior, says Eliot Cohen, the Robert E. Osgood Professor of Strategic Studies at the Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies. Congressmen say they can't imagine U.S. troops committing the kinds of atrocities recorded at the Abu Ghraib prison in Iraq; left-leaning anti-war advocates at Moveon.org refer to General David Petraeus, the highly regarded commander of the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan, as General Betray Us. More than that, a large gap between those who make the decisions about war and those who fight it raises serious questions about accountability. The Vietnam-era draft inspired thousands of Americans to push back against Washington's decisions to expand the war. Conversely, the existence of the all volunteer army, in effect since 1973, may have one been one reason for the relatively smaller level of protest in the run up to, and the execution of the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq. Indeed, at a 2006 Oval Office meeting with President George W. Bush, Kennedy said the president told him that if the draft had been in place he "would have been impeached by now."
      The gap also raises concerns about civic unity. Earth-shaking events such as World War II and Sept. 11 brought citizens together, says Jean Bethke Elshtain, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Professor of Social and Political Ethics in the Divinity School at the University of Chicago. But sustaining that unity is extremely difficult, and becomes even more so when one segment of the population is willing to give its life to protect Americans while the vast majority go on with their lives without making any sacrifice of their own. To Elshtain, this raises a basic issue of fairness and social justice. There is a general lack of equity, she says, when "some families bear a radically disproportionate burden of service and sacrifice." As their peers "study or work or frolic, they die" in Iraq or Afghanistan.
      Redressing this imbalance is an extraordinary challenge. Surely a draft would help. But it raises ethical questions of its own. There is also no political will to reinstate it. Nor, says Cohen, is it necessary or even desirable from a military perspective. A better set of solutions, he suggests, would start with expanding the depth and scope of relations between civilians and military personnel. He recommends siting military bases around the country so that civilians in New England, say, where there is virtually no military presence, can have greater exposure to an institution about which many of them know very little. Elite universities such as Stanford and Harvard, which have long prohibited on-campus ROTC activities, should start revisiting and revising their policies so that over time the military will have a wider diversity of background. Doing so might enrich the campus experience, and it could also lead to a stronger military in which the highly educated graduates of America's elite educational institutions would take a greater role influencing America's elite military institutions. For now, Kennedy observes, we have effectively "hired some of the least advantaged of our fellow countrymen to do some of our most dangerous business." And we continue down this path at our peril.
    - Lewis, John 80th birthday, 2010 Nov 4; 399 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - Orientation, 2009 Oct 5; 167 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - Orientation, 2010 Sep 27; 108 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - Political Science 212S simulation, 2012 May 21; 107 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - POLISCI 22SC: The Face of Battle (Little Bighorn), 2012; 987 computer file(s) (jpg)
      INSTRUCTORS Scott D. Sagan - Stanford University Joseph Felter - Stanford University
      Our understanding of warfare often derives from the lofty perspective of political leaders and generals: what were their objectives and what strategies were developed to meet them? This top-down perspective slights the experience of the actual combatants and non-combatants caught in the crossfire. This course focuses on the complexity of the process by which strategy is translated into tactical decisions by the officers and foot soldiers on the field of battle. We will focus on three battles in American history: Gettysburg (July 1863), the Battle of Little Bighorn (June 1876), and the Korengal Valley campaign in Afghanistan (2006-2010). In addition to reading major works on these battles and the conflicts in which they occurred, we will travel to Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, and the Little Bighorn battlefield in Montana. The course¿s battlefield tours are based on the ¿staff rides¿ developed by the Prussian Army in the mid-1800s and employed by the U.S. Army since the early 1900s. While at Stanford, students will conduct extensive research on individual participants at Gettysburg and Little Bighorn. Then, as we walk through the battlefield sites, students will brief the group on their subjects' experience of battle and on why they made the decisions they did during the conflict. Why did Lt. General Longstreet oppose the Confederate attack on the Union Army at Gettysburg? What was the experience of a military surgeon on a Civil War battlefield? Why did Custer divide his 7th Cavalry troops as they approached the Little Bighorn River? What was the role of Lakota Sioux women after a battle? Travel will be provided and paid by Sophomore College (except incidentals) and is made possible by the support of the Center for International Security and Cooperation (CISAC).
      Grubbs, David.
    - Sagan, Scott celebration, 2011 Oct 24; 282 computer file(s) (jpg)
    - Book Launch for Philip Taubman's ''The Partnership: Five Cold Warriors and Their Quest to Ban the Bomb", 2012 Jan 25; 95 computer file(s) (jpg)